Finding Aid for John Robert Crouse papers, 1905-1932
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
John Robert Crouse papers 1905-1932
Crouse, John Robert, 1874-1946.
7 linear feet
851054 Aa 2
Promoter of electricity, founder of the Society for Electrical Development, and supporter of the principle of cooperation in electricity and other industries; miscellaneous materials relating to the electrical industry.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was transferred from the Cromaine Branch of the Hartland Public Library (donor no. 5435 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
John Robert Crouse, Sr., was born January 1, 1874 in Hartland, Michigan, son of John Bernard and Betsy Westfall Crouse. His early childhood was spent in Hartland. He moved to Cleveland, Ohio with his family, where he graduated from Central High School of Cleveland in 1893. After graduation from the University of Michigan in 1897 he joined his father, J.B. Crouse, and his uncle, H.A. Tremaine, in Ohio in the Fostoria Incandescent Lamp Company.
In 1901 they created the National Electric Lamp Association which eventually merged with General Electric. Crouse's greatest contribution to the electrical industry was his vision of cooperation. He worked hard for this ideal as founder and director of the Society for Electrical Development and in working to bring together into a cooperative organization the manufacturers of electric refrigerators.
Crouse had many other business and philanthropic interests, including the establishment of the Waldenwoods cooperative camp located near Hartland, Michigan. He died July 18, 1946.
The Crouse collection relates primarily to his interest in electrical development and cooperation. Include are minutes of the Advisory Board of the National Lamp Works of the General Electric Company, publications of the Society for Electrical Development, bulletins of the Cooperative Electrical Development, and printed materials. There are also some materials concerning his philanthropic endeavors.
Subjects:
Association Island (N.Y.); Camp Co-operation (Association Island, N.Y.); Cooperative Electrical Development.; Cooperative societies--United States.; Electric industries.; General Electric Company.; Hartland (Mich.); Livingston County (Mich.); National Lamp Works.; Society for Electrical Development.; Waldenwoods (Hartland, Mich.)
- Electrical industry
  - Minutes Annual Review by The Advisory Board of H.O. Departments (National Lamp Works of General Electric)
    - 1912-1915 (Box 1)
    - 1915-1916. (Box 2)
  - Books: The Story of Electricity, 2 volumes (Box 2)
  - Society for Electrical Development publications (Box 3)
  - National Electric Light Association Conventions, 1905-1907 (Box 4)
  - Nela Series (1-35) (Box 4)
  - Cooperative Electrical Development Bulletins, 1906-1907 (Box 5)
  - Cooperative Electrical Development Bulletins, 1906-1907 (Box 6)
  - History of the Cooperative Movement in the Electrical Business, 1932 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous printed materials concerning electricity and the Waldenwoods cooperative movement (Box 6)
  - Industrial Library (Box 6)
- Other interests
  - Camp Co-operation miscellanea (Box 7)
  - Correspondence (Box 7)
  - Photograph albums (Box 7)